Mss.B.H88
American Philosophical Society
Alexander von Humboldt papers, 1801-1859
1793-1859
Mss.B.H88
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet Ca. 250 items
This collection contains miscellaneous letters and papers relating to explorations of South America, Cuba, and Mexico; scientific investigations; Latin American antiquities and linguistics; and publications. There are also copies of 26 letters from Humboldt to Pierre Hyacinth Azais and Jules Berger de Xivrey, from originals at the Duke University Medical Center Library.
Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
Box 1
General note
For articles regarding parts of this collection, see Helmut de Terra, "Alexander von Humboldt's Correspondence with Jefferson, Madison, and Gallatin," American Philosophical Society Proceedings 103 (1959): 783 and "Studies of the Documentation of Alexander von Humboldt," APS Proceedings 102 (1958): 136, 560.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Received and accessioned, 1957. See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers and dates.
Biographical/Historical note
Alexander von Humboldt was a traveler and naturalist. In 1799 he traveled to Spanish America, where he explored and collected geological, zoological, and botanical specimens for five years.
Naval History Note
The Alexander von Humboldt Papers contain at least one letter which may be of interest to naval historians:
Humboldt, Alexander von. Letter to Matthew Fontaine Maury. n.d. Concerning his work on hydrography, refers to Gay-Lussac. 2 pages. (B H88.39).
Early American History Note
This collection of Humboldt’s correspondence touches on his travels throughout the Americas. Of note are his letters with prominent Americans--namely Thomas Jefferson, Rembrandt Peale, and Peter Du Ponceau--about his observations. Many letters are in French. Some have translations.
There are also other documents that relate to Humboldt’s activities, such as a record of his arrival at the Philadelphia customs house and various other letters to scientific luminaries of the day.
The APS also has photocopies and other reproductions of Humboldt’s correspondence, including letters to Albert Gallatin.
Azaïs, Pierre Hyacinthe, 1766-1845; Berger de Xivrey, Jules, 1801-1863; Buckland, William, 1784-1856; Coquerel, Athanase, 1795-1868; Correia da Serra, José Francisco, 1750-1823; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844; Frederick William -- IV, -- King of Prussia, -- 1795-1861.; Gaggiotti-Richards, Emma, 1825-1912; Galunsky, Louis Charles; Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, Isidore, 1805-1861; Horner, Leonard, 1785-1864; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Jomard, M., (Edme-François), 1777-1862; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Michaux, André, 1746-1802; Pickersgill, Henry William, 1782-1875; Sabine, Edward, Sir, 1788-1883; Schlagintweit-Sakünlunski, Hermann Rudolph Alfred von, -- 1826-1882.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Waagen, Gustav Friedrich, 1794-1868; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845; Willdenow, Karl Ludwig, 1765-1812; General Correspondence; Natural history.; Science and Technology; Science publishing.; Scientific expeditions.; South America -- Discovery and exploration -- 19th century.; Travel; Travel Narratives and Journals
- Papers
  - Poem to Alexander von Humboldt, Jan. 22, 1793; 4-1/2x7; Cettzet, L
    Scope and Contents note
    Frankfurt, A.D.S. 1p., end. In German. Mentioned in: de Terra. Humboldt, pp.66-67, fn. Old Call Number: B H88.x1
  - Letter to Jules François Paul Fauris de Saint-Vincens, Aix, Jan.5, 1797; Humboldt, Wilhelm, Freiherr von, 1767-1835
    Paris, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. In French. Concerning his study of languages. Refers to his son. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.19
  - Letter to Karl Ludwig Willdenow, Berlin, March 4, 1801; 9x7-1/4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Havana, A.L.S. 2p. and.add. In German. Old Call Number: B H88.23
  - Letter to the governor of Jaén, Jan. 18, 1803; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Guayaquil, Photostat of A.L.S. 4p. In Spanish. From original in American Museum of Natural History. ---- Translation typed by Dr. R. C. Murphy. Concerning botany and Lima, Peru. Old Call Number: B H88.19
  - Baggage entry statement to the U.S. Customs, May 24, 1804; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Philadelphia, Printed D. filled in in ms. S. 1p. and end. Baggage entry statement to the U.S. Customs.
  - Letter to Mrs. Hannah Nicholson Gallatin, June 6, 1804; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849
    Washington, Photo.of A.L.S. 4p. Loving, paternal letter. Tells of his meeting with Humboldt and comments on the man's generosity and knowledge. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Diary, 1804; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Voyage from Cuba to Philadelphia; Photostat of A.D. 9 leaves. From original in possession [May, 1961] of the Deutsche Staatsbibliothek, Berlin. Presented by Helmut de Terra,grantee; May 1961. Old Call Number: B H88.42
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, June 20, 1804; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Philadelphia, Photo. of A.L.S. 3p., end. In French. Thank you letter. Lists sailing dat and sends forwarding address for material which Gallatin has promised him. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, Washington, June 27, 1804; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Philadelphia, Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. In French. Thanks for his memoir. Concerning the U.S. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Gotthilf Henry Ernest Mühlenberg, June 27, 1804; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Philadelphia, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. In German. (from original in Lutheran Theological Seminary, Germantown.) Printed: A.P.S. Proceeds, v.92, no.2, p.109. Old Call Number: B H88.14
  - Letter to Joseph Carrington Cabell, March 1805; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Xerox of A.L. in 3rd P. 1p. and add. In French. Will accompany Cabell and Irving to the home of the Imperial Minister. Presented by of Va. Library; February 1973. Old Call Number: B H88.102
  - Mes Confessions, 1805; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    ca. Xerox of A.D.S. 4p. In French. From original in Possession of the Bibliotheque Municipal et Universitaire at Geneva. Autobiographical memoir. Presented by the BMU, Geneva; January 24, 1973. Old Call Number: B H88.99
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, March 1, 1809; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.in 3rd.P. 1p. and add. In French. Concerning a meeting with friends at Kotschuboy [Kotzebue?]. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.1
  - Letter to Rembrandt Peale, Sept. 15, 1810; 5-3/4x6; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p. In French. Regrets not seeing him. Wants him to forward the Indian material. Refers to C. W. Peale. Old Call Number: B H88.54
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, Dec. 26, 1811; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Introduces Correa de Serra. Asks for some things to be shipped him. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 29, 1811; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. In German. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.21
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, March 10, 1812; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 3p. and end. In French. Concerning the publication of Pike's Misissippi travels. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, July 16, 1813; 9x7; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. In French. Praises his work on Egypt. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.2
  - Letter to Jean Phillippe François, 1753-1835, April 5, 1814; Deleuze, J. P. F. (Joseph Philippe François), 1753-1835
    Humboldt, [Alexander, i.e., Friedrich Wilhelm Heinrich Alexander, freiherr von], 1769-1859. Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Friendly letter. Old Call Number: B H88. 11 no. 5
  - Letter to Jean Phillippe François Deleuze, April 5, 1814; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Friendly letter. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.5
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, May, 1815; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Invitation to a gathering. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.3
  - Letter to ----, 1815; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 2p. In French. Old Call Number: B H88.106
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, 1815?; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Jeudi. Photo. of A.L.S. 4p.,end. In French. Concerning the War of 1812. Refers to Jefferson, Warden and Gay-Lussac. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, June 2, 1816; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. In French. Thanks him for his compliments, but suggests he quote a review of his works. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, July 19, 1816; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 3p. and end. In French. Concerning his publication. Refers to Maskell. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, Sept. 24, 1816; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L. 1p. and end. In French. Has written Jefferson and Madison for him. Refers to Gay Lussac. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to ----, Sept. 24, 1816; 9x7-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning the purchase of publications. Old Call Number: B H88.10
  - Letter to P. H. (Pierre Hyacinthe) Azais, Dec. 27, 1816; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Dec. 30, 1816; 7-1/2x4-3/4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Sends him prints. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.4
  - Answers to botanical questions asked by Humboldt, 1817; Brown, Robert, 1773-1858
    Photostat of A.D. 4p. (from original in British Museum, Natural history.) Old Call Number: B H88.16 no.6
  - List of questions on botany addressed to Robert Brown, 1817?; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photostat of A.D.S. 4p. In French. (from original in British Museum, Natural history.) Old Call Number: B H88.16 no.5
  - Letter to P. H. (Pierre Hyacinthe) Azais, Jan. 13, 1818; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to P. H. (Pierre Hyacinthe) Azais, Feb. 15, 1818; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to P. H. (Pierre Hyacinthe) Azais, July 19, 1818; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Aug. 24, 1818; 5x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Asks him question concerning Egypt. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.5
  - Letter to Monsieur Perry, Aug. 27, 1818; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. In French. Friendly letter. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.13
  - Letter to Alexander von Humboldt, Paris, Dec. 9, 1818; Thénard, Louis Jacques, baron, 1777-1857
    Photo. of A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Wishes to send map to the person he recommended [Gallatin]. Enclosed originally in: Humboldt to Gallatin; [Dec. 1818]. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, Dec., 1818; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Jeudi []. Photo. of A.L.S. 1p. and end. In French. Enc. Hopes he has received the note from Thénard. For enclosure, see: Thénard to Humboldt; Dec.9, 1818. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, August, 1819; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Mercredi. Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and add. ,end. In French. Concerning Charles Coqueville. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, Sept., 1819; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Mardi []. Photo. of A.L.S. 3p. and end. In French. Questions on weights and measures. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, Nov., 1819; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Dimanche. Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and end. Enc. In French. Gives letter of introduction for Brongniart. For enclosure, see: Humboldt to Brongniart; [Nov.1819] Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Sept. 13, 1819; 4-1/2x3-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 3p. In French. Concerning hieroglyphics. Friendly letter. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.6
  - Letter to Alexander Brongniart, Nov., 1819; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Dimanche. Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Introduces Albert Gallatin. Enclosed originally in: Humboldt to Gallatin; [Nov.1819]. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Sophie Duvaucel, Nov. 27, 1820; 4-3/4x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. with initial. 4p. and add.,end. In French. "Chez M.le B[aro]n Cuvier" Friendly letter. Old Call Number: B H88.15 no.1
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, Jan. 24, 1820; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. In French. Thanks him for all the work he has done in publications. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to ----, Dec. 1, 1820; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p., end. In French. Concerning a correction for his work. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.17
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Jan. 19, 1821; 5x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Refuses invitation. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.7
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, July 31, 1821; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Lundi []. Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and end. In French. Sets date for visit with him, De Candolle and Arago. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to le Comte de Tul(?), May 6, 1822; 3-1/4x6-1/4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, A.L. in 3rd. P. 1p. In French. Regrets they cannot do as he wishes. Old Call Number: B H88.15 no.2
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, 1822; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Mardi. Photo.of A.L.S. 2p. In French. Recommends a teacher. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, 1822; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Mercredi. Photo.of A.L.S. 1p., end. In French. Asks question about a publication. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to James Pound, Greenwich, April 20, 1823; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Concerning Gautier. Daguerre photograph on additional page. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.11
  - Letter to Albert Gallatin, May, 1823; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Mardi. Photo. of A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. In French. Will dine with him. Sends two volumes on the Iroquois language. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to ----, June 4, 1823; 7-1/2x5; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. In French. Asks if he will help two young compatriots. Old Call Number: B H88.63
  - Letter to M. Tardieu, Aug. 13, 1823; 5x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Would like to help them with their dictionary but is very busy. Old Call Number: B H88.49
  - Note, 1823; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.D. 4p. In French. Concerning South and Central America. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, 1823?; 5x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Samedi. A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Thanks for his works. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.8
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Feb. 27, 1824; 10x8; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Awaits plates for his publication on heiroglyphics for a friend. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.9
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, June 23, 1824?; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Thank you note. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to ----, 1824; 5x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 3p. In French. Old Call Number: B H88.3
  - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, Feb. 22, 1825; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, Photostat of A.L. 2p., end. In French. (from original in possession of the Mass. Historical society.) Friendly letter. Old Call Number: B H88.6
  - Letter to Robert Brown?, Sept. 1, 1825; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and end. In French. From original in British Musuem, Natural history. Introduces friends. Old Call Number: B H88.16 no.4
  - Letter to Sir James Mackintosh, September 1, 1825; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p. In French. Thanks for information. Recommends Gans and Hotho. His Voyage and adverse criticism to it in England. Old Call Number: B H88.73
  - Letter to Marc Antoine Jullien [de Paris], Sept. 21, 1825; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photostat of A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Concerning his publications. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.3
  - Letter to Adriano Balbi, Oct. 10, 1825; 5x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Sunday []. A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Old Call Number: B H88.20 no.6
  - Letter to Christian[?] Lassen, Nov., 1825; 5x4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Friday. A.L.S. 3p. and add. In German. Old Call Number: B H88.15 no.3
  - Distribution de la médaille du sacre, 1825; B H88a; 1.0 Volume(s); 12-3/4x8-1/2; Institut de France
    D.S.: G. Cuvier and 28 others. 1p. (see Agassiz. Address... Humboldt, p.38.)
  - Letter to ----, Jan. 6, 1826; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Responding to a dinner invitation to "not next Thursday..." Old Call Number: B H88.79
  - Letter to Jules Berger de Xivrey, April 1, 1826; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, April 15, 1826; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. In French. Concerning old culture of Guatemala and Oaxaca, Mexico. Refers to plates of Palenque bas-relief. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to Jules Berger de Xivrey, April 19, 1826; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to Jules Berger de Xivrey, Dec. 31, 1826; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to ----, March 15, 1827; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, A.L.S. 4p., end. In French. Concerning work on geography of Mexico and South America. Scientific news. Old Call Number: B H88.78
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, April 18, 1827?; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Criticizes publication for discrepancies in area of U.S. and size of Indian population. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to William Buckland, April 26, 1827; 7x4-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Copy. Friendly letter. Concerning atmospheric pressure. Old Call Number: B H88.22
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, Dec., 1827?; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Jeudi [Thursday]. Photo.of A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. In French. Asks question. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, 1827; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Concerning size of lake in Nicaragua. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to Benjamin Guy Babington, June 29, 1828; Humboldt, Wilhelm, Freiherr von, 1767-1835
    Photo. of L. in 3rd. P. 3p. Concerning Ellis' dissertation on an Indian language. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.16
  - Letter to Coronel [sic] William Duane, Philadelphia, Aug. 21, 1828; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Caracas, Photo. of copy of L. 2p. Asks for almanacs for 1829. Concerning South America. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Friedrich August Rosen, Detmold, July 22, 1829; Humboldt, Wilhelm, Freiherr von, 1767-1835
    Photostatt of A.L.S. 3p. and add. In German. Old Call Number: B H88.11 no.22
  - Letter to William Brose, April 10, 1829; 10x8; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 2p. and end. In French. Asks for advice for a map engraver. Explains dreadful handwriting, due to rheumatism caught while sleeping on the ground in South America. Old Call Number: B H88.72
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Nov. 8, 1831?; 7-1/2x5-1/4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Thanks for his deeds. Refers to Ferussac. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.10
  - Letter to Charles Bresson, 1831; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 2p. and env. Asks Bresson to superintend the shipment of some physics memoirs to the Academie des Sciences. Old Call Number: B H88.105
  - Concerning the telegraph, Feb. 1, 1832; 11x8; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Paris, A.D.S. 1p. In French. Old Call Number: B H88.60
  - Letter to "Monsieur le Directeur General", Feb. 1, 1832; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Comments on "la Telegraphie." Old Call Number: B H88.96
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, April 26, 1833; 10x8; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p. In French. Concerning a friend. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.11
  - Letter to Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, Nov. 18, 1833; 8x6-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 2p., end. In French. Concerning his work on scientific subjects, geology, paleontology, etc. Old Call Number: B H88.44
  - Letter to Gabriel Valentin, Jan. 30, 1835; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to Augustus Frederick, Duke of Sussex, President of the Royal Society of London, April 23, 1835; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, Photo. of L.S. 19 leaves. In French. From microfilm copy - Film 870.1. Original is at Royal Society of London. Proposal for earthwide study of terrestrial magnetism. Old Call Number: B H88.37
  - Letter to Jules Berger de Xivrey, Oct. 14, 1835; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, Oct. 19, 1835; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 1p., end. and add. In French. Asks location of Fort Vancouver. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to David Bailie Warden, Oct., 1835; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Photo. of A.L.S. 1p., end. and add. In French. Thanks him for his work. FOR REFERENCE USE ONLY. Old Call Number: B H88.36
  - Letter to Alexander von Humboldt, Sept. 12, 1836; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849
    New York, Photo. of A.L. 1p. and end. In French. Asked R. M. Patterson, Renwick to answer his queries on gold. Old Call Number: B H88.1
  - Letter to Jules Berger de Xivrey, Dec. 3, 1836; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to William Clift, Aug. 10, 1837; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. (From original in British Museum, natural history.) Introduces Prof. Dictenbach. Old Call Number: B H88.16 no.3
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Jan. 9, 1837; 8-3/4x5-1/4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p., end. In French. Thought of him while travelling in Asia. Geology. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.12
  - Letter to ----, May 3, 1837; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
  - Letter to Henry Wheaton, June 10, 1837; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, Photo. of L. 3p. Copy. Gold production in the U.S.and Russia. Presented by Helmut de Terra, grantee, Nov. 1960. Old Call Number: B H88.38 Film 8
  - Letter to Dr. Ortila, March 4, 1838; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Asks him to help Koreff. Old Call Number: B H88.92
  - Letter to Monsieur Cuvier, Paris, May. 28, 1838; 10-1/2x8-3/4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    Berlin, A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Introduces Mr. Hanstein. Old Call Number: B H88.68
  - Letter to Edmé François Jomard, Paris, July 20, 1838; 10-1/2x9; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. In French. Introduces Ehrenberg. Old Call Number: B H88.4 no.13
  - Letter to Professor Valenciennes, Oct. 27, 1838; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Pathological news. Refers to Gay-Lussac and Geoffroy St. Hilaire. Old Call Number: B H88.59 No.1
  - Letter to Madame la comtesse, Oct. 21, 1838; 10x7-1/2; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859